Sam Tobin-Hochstadt

School of Informatics & Computing Indiana University 150 S. Woodlawn Ave. Bloomington, IN 47405 215E Lindley Hall

samth@cs.indiana.edu
homes.soic.indiana.edu/samth

Research Interests

My research focuses on the design and analysis of software and programming languages. I am particularly interested in how programs grow from prototype scripts to robust software, and how programming language design can support this process. My research concerns type systems, software contracts, modularity, and extensibility.

Appointments

| 2013— | Assistant Professor, School of Informatics and Computing, Indiana University |
|--|--|
| 2011—2013 2009—2011 2003—2009 2004—2006 | Research Assistant Professor, CCIS, Northeastern University Mozilla Postdoctoral Research Fellow, CCIS, Northeastern University Research & Teaching Assistant, CCIS, Northeastern University Intern, Programming Languages Research Group, Sun Microsystems Labs |
| | Education |
| 2010 | Ph.D in Computer Science, Northeastern University Thesis title: Typed Scheme: From Scripts to Programs Received CCIS Outstanding Research Award |
| 2006 | MA in Computer Science, Northeastern University |
| 2003 | BS in Computer Science with Honors, University of Chicago |
| | Grants |
| 2012—2015 | Behavioral Software Contract Verification, Principal Investigator (Co-PI David Van Horn). Grant awarded by NSF Division of Computer and Communication Foundations. \$399,992 |
| 2011—2012 | Gift from the Mozilla Foundation, \$74,900 |
| 2009—2011 | 2-year Mozilla Research Fellowship, Mozilla Foundation, \$200,000 |
| | Publications: Journals & Selective Conferences |
| 2013 | The Design and Implementation of Typed Scheme, with Matthias Felleisen, <i>Higher Order and Symbolic Computation (HOSC)</i> , to appear. |
| 2013 | Constraining Delimited Control with Contracts, with Asumu Takikawa and T. Stephen Strickland, <i>Proc. of the 22nd European Symposium on Programming (ESOP)</i> . |
| 2012 | Gradual Typing for First-Class Classes, with Asumu Takikawa, T. Stephen Strickland, Christos Dimoulas, and Matthias Felleisen, <i>Proc. of the 2012 ACM Conference on Object Oriented Programming Systems, Languages, and Applications (OOPSLA)</i> . Best Student Paper |

- 2012 Higher-Order Symbolic Execution via Contracts, with David Van Horn, *Proc. of the 2012 ACM Conference on Object Oriented Programming Systems, Languages, and Applications (OOPSLA).*
- Optimization Coaching, with Vincent St-Amour and Matthias Felleisen, Proc. of the 2012 ACM Conference on Object Oriented Programming Systems, Languages, and Applications (OOPSLA).
- 2012 Chaperones and Impersonators: Runtime Support for Reasonable Interposition, with T. Stephen Strickland, Robert Bruce Findler, and Matthew Flatt, *Proc. of the 2012 ACM Conference on Object Oriented Programming Systems, Languages, and Applications (OOPSLA).*
- 2012 Complete Monitoring for Behavioral Contracts, with Christos Dimoulas and Matthias Felleisen, Proc. 21st European Symposium on Programming (ESOP).
- 2012 Run Your Research: On the Effectiveness of Lightweight Mechanization, with Casey Klein, John Clements, Christos Dimoulas, Carl Eastlund, Matthias Felleisen, Matthew Flatt, Jay A. McCarthy, Jon Rafkind, and Robert Bruce Findler, *Proc. 39th ACM Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages (POPL)*.
- Typing the Numeric Tower, with Vincent St-Amour, Matthew Flatt, and Matthias Felleisen, 2012 Symposium on Practical Aspects of Declarative Languages (PADL).
- 2011 Languages as Libraries, with Vincent St-Amour, Ryan Culpepper, Matthew Flatt, and Matthias Felleisen, Proc. 32nd ACM Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI).
- 2010 Logical Types for Untyped Languages, with Matthias Felleisen, *Proc. 15th ACM International Conference on Functional Programming (ICFP)*.
- 2009 Practical Variable-Arity Polymorphism, with Matthias Felleisen and T. Stephen Strickland, Proc. Eighteenth European Symposium on Programming (ESOP).
- The Design and Implementation of Typed Scheme, with Matthias Felleisen, *Proc. 35th ACM Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages (POPL)*.
- 2006 Interlanguage Migration: From Scripts to Programs, with Matthias Felleisen, *Dynamic Languages Symposium at OOPSLA (DLS)*.

Publications: Workshops & Technical Reports

- 2011 Semantic Solutions to Program Analysis Problems (Abstract), with David Van Horn, 2011 Fun Ideas and Thoughts Session at the 32nd ACM Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (FIT).
- 2010 Extensible Pattern Matching for Extensible Languages (Abstract), 2010 Symposium on Implementation and Application of Functional Languages (IFL).
- 2010 Where are you going with those types? (Abstract), with Vincent St-Amour, Matthias Felleisen, and Matthew Flatt, 2010 Symposium on Implementation and Application of Functional Languages (IFL).
- 2010 Purely Functional Data Structures for Typed Racket, with Hari Prashanth K R, 2010 Workshop on Scheme and Functional Programming.
- 2009 Cycles without pollution: a gradual typing poem, with Robert Bruce Findler, First Workshop on Script to Program Evolution (STOP).
- 2007 Advanced Macrology and the Implementation of Typed Scheme, with Ryan Culpepper and Matthew Flatt, 2007 Workshop on Scheme and Functional Programming.
- A Core Calculus of Metaclasses, with Eric Allen, Twelfth Workshop on Foundations of Object-Oriented Languages (FOOL).

2004—2008 Fortress Language Specification, with Eric Allen, David Chase, Joe Hallet, Victor Luchangco, Jan-Willem Maessen, Sukyoung Ryu, and Guy L. Steele Jr., versions 0.618-1.0, Sun Microsystems Technical Report.

Patents

Method and apparatus for expressing and checking relationships between types, with Sukyoung Ryu, Eric Allen, Victor Luchangco, and Joe Hallet, US Patent 8,225,294.

Teaching

At Indiana

2013 Object-Oriented Software Development

At Northeastern

| 2013 | Instructor, Fundamentals of Computer Science 2 (Honors) |
|-------------|---|
| 2012 | Instructor, Fundamentals of Computer Science 2 (Honors) |
| 2011 | Instructor, Fundamentals of Computer Science 2 (Honors) |
| 2009 | Instructor, Fundamentals of Computer Science 1 |
| 2005 | Instructor, Fundamentals of Computer Science 2 |
| 2003 - 2008 | Teaching Assistant, Fundamentals of CS 1 (2003, 2004), Fundamentals of CS 2 (2004), |
| | Software Development (2005), Programming Languages (2006, 2008) |

Students

| 2011— | Tony Garnock-Jones, Ph.D student, Northeastern University (Co-advisor) |
|-----------|--|
| 2010— | Vincent St-Amour, Ph.D student, Northeastern University (Co-advisor) |
| 2012— | Phil Nguyen, MS student, Northeastern University |
| 2009—2011 | Hari Prashanth K R, MS Thesis, Northeastern University |
| 2007 | Ivan Gazeau, Ph.D student from École normale supérieure (Paris) |

Selected Talks

| 2013 | From Principles to Practice with Class in the First Year. OOPSLA PC Meeting Workshop |
|------|--|
| 2013 | Evolving Software from Scripts to Programs. ETH Zurich Department of Computer Science, |
| | Indiana University Department of Computer Science, Iowa State University Software En- |
| | gineering Seminar, University of Idaho Department of Computer Science |
| 2012 | Research meets Application: Life on the EcmaScript Committee. Northeastern University |
| | Ph.D Seminar |
| 2012 | Occurrence Typing. Dagstuhl meeting on Foundation of Scripting Languages |
| 2012 | Languages as Libraries. Dagstuhl meeting on Foundation of Scripting Languages |
| 2011 | Domain-Specific Languages for GnoSys. DARPA CRASH PI Meeting |
| 2011 | Evolving Software from Scripts to Programs. Oregon State University Department of Com- |
| | puter Science |
| 2010 | From Scripts to Programs. Indiana University Department of Computer Science |
| 2010 | Logical Types for Scheme. New England Programming Languages and Systems Symposium |

| Seminar Types for Scheme, in Scheme. Boston Lisp Meeting Typed Scheme: From Scripts to Programs. Sun Microsystems Laboratories The Design and Implementation of Typed Scheme. Symposium in Honor of Mitchell Wand To Type or Not to Type. Northeastern University ACM Lecture Series | |
|--|--|
| Typed Scheme: From Scripts to Programs. Sun Microsystems Laboratories The Design and Implementation of Typed Scheme. Symposium in Honor of Mitchell Wand To Type or Not to Type. Northeastern University ACM Lecture Series | |
| The Design and Implementation of Typed Scheme. Symposium in Honor of Mitchell Wand To Type or Not to Type. Northeastern University ACM Lecture Series | |
| 2008 To Type or Not to Type. Northeastern University ACM Lecture Series | |
| | |
| | |
| Professional Activities | |
| Cump saint on Implementation and Application of Eurotional Languages Chair | |
| Symposium on Implementation and Application of Functional Languages, Chair | |
| 2013—2014 International Conference on Functional Programming, Workshop Co-Chair | |
| Foundations of Software Engineering 2013 New Ideas Track, Program Committee | |
| 2013 SPLASH: OOPSLA, Program Committee | |
| 2012 Dynamic Languages Symposium, Program Committee | |
| 2012 International Conference on Functional Programming, Program Committee | |
| 2012 Workshop on Script to Program Evolution, Chair | |
| 2010—2013 TC39 - ECMAScript (Standards Committee for JavaScript), Member | |
| 2011 Workshop on Scheme and Functional Programming, Program Committee | |
| New England Programming Languages and Systems Symposium, Chair | |
| 2011 Workshop on Script to Program Evolution, Program Committee | |
| 2011 Workshop on Types in Language Design and Implementation, Program Committee | |
| 2010 Workshop on Foundations of Object-Oriented Languages, Program Committee | |
| Symposium on Trends in Functional Programming, Program Committee | |

Reviewer for J. of Functional Programming, ESOP 2013, POPL 2013, OOPSLA 2012, ECOOP 2012, VMCAI 2012, OOPSLA 2009, ICFP 2008

Professional Associations

Association for Computing Machinery, SIGPLAN